<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: visual studio | bling on software development]]></title>
  <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/categories/visual-studio/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bling.github.io//"/>
  <updated>2013-06-05T01:50:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bling.github.io//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bailey Ling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tools I Use To Do What I Do]]></title>
    <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/2011/06/23/tools-i-use-to-do-what-i-do/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bling.github.io//blog/2011/06/23/tools-i-use-to-do-what-i-do</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>It’s been a while since I last blogged, but I want to get back into it….I just haven’t thought about what I wanna blog about yet.&nbsp; I’m thinking of doing some sort of multi-part series on a topic but haven’t decided on what yet.&nbsp; Nonetheless, just to get the ball rolling again here’s a quick blog post on some of the tools I use to do my every day job that’s in addition to your typical .NET developer tool chain.</p> <p><strong>General</strong></p> <p><a href="http://www.tcbmi.com/strokeit/">StrokeIt</a>:&nbsp; Funny name aside, on any clean install of Windows this is the <strong>first</strong> thing I install.&nbsp; I load up IE and I download this, followed by Chrome/Firefox.&nbsp; It is a mouse gesture program that affects all of Windows.&nbsp; By holding down the right mouse button, and making gestures you can do common tasks like minimize (drag SW), maximize (drag NE), close (draw a C), and others.&nbsp; It’s much faster than clicking the minimize/maximize buttons.&nbsp; For web browsing, creating and close tabs are drag SE and drag NW respectively.&nbsp; Back is W.&nbsp; Forward is E.&nbsp; Working this way is faster than any keyboard shortcut.</p> <p><a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/console/">Console2</a>:&nbsp; It’s not a necessity, but it’s nice to be able to use a console with a better looking font.&nbsp; You can easily customize to run another shell, and in my case I have Powershell as the shell.</p> <p><a href="http://virtuawin.sourceforge.net/">VirtuaWin</a>:&nbsp; Ironically I don’t use any virtual desktops, but this app creates a nice middle click on any window that lets you mark it as ‘always on top’.</p> <p><a href="http://www.vim.org/">Vim</a>:&nbsp; It was an awful, painful 2 weeks to learn this thing but I’m sure glad I did.</p> <p><strong>Development/Visual Studio</strong></p> <p><a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/resharper/">Resharper</a>:&nbsp; This one doesn’t need much mentioning as anyone serious about programming in .NET has either heard of it, use it, or use one of its competitors like <a href="http://www.devexpress.com/Products/Visual_Studio_Add-in/Coding_Assistance/">CodeRush</a>.</p> <p><a href="http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/465a0d53-5133-4edd-a0cd-94484fe3d853">AllMargins</a>:&nbsp; This hidden gem is an awesome extension has brings a bunch of very useful features to the editor.&nbsp; It brings structural highlighting, highlighting matching words under caret, and RockScroll inspired scroll bar, and it does it all with little to no cost in performance.</p> <p><a href="http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/d0d33361-18e2-46c0-8ff2-4adea1e34fef/">Productivity Power Tools</a>:&nbsp; There’s only 2 that I use here: document tabs, and moving lines.&nbsp; All the rest are either eye candy, negligible enhancements, or just plain too slow to be any use in large solutions (solution navigator I’m looking at you!!).</p> <p><a href="http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/1a67eee3-fdd1-4745-b290-09d649d07ee0">XAML Intellisense Presenter</a>:&nbsp; This is a must-have for anyone who works with XAML in VS regularly.&nbsp; Resharper 6 may soon make this obsolete, however…</p> <p><a href="http://wiki.sharpdevelop.net/ILSpy.ashx">ILSpy</a>/<a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/decompiler/">dotPeek</a>:&nbsp; Decompilers.&nbsp; ‘nuff said.</p> <p><a href="http://snoopwpf.codeplex.com/">Snoop</a>:&nbsp; Staple tool for WPF developers to inspect the visual/logical tree.&nbsp; There’s also <a href="http://wpfinspector.codeplex.com/">WPF Inspector</a> which has a much nicer UI, but unfortunately doesn’t perform as fast.</p> <p><strong>Profiling</strong></p> <p><a href="http://www.red-gate.com/products/dotnet-development/dotnet-developer-bundle/">ANTS</a>/<a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/profiler/">dotTrace</a>/<a href="http://www.yourkit.com/dotnet/download/">YourKit</a>/etc:&nbsp; I’ve used many performance/memory profilers, and those 3 are the ones I like the most.&nbsp; Unfortunately, they all do things the others don’t, and all these things are very useful, so you still end up needing to use all of them to fix the particular problem you’re working on.</p> <p><a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463009">WinDbg</a>: It isn’t every day I use this, but I’m sure glad to know that such a thing exists and the amount of power it gives me.</p> <p><strong>Scripting</strong></p> <p><a href="http://powergui.org/index.jspa">PowerGUI</a>:&nbsp; Best tool I found for editing PowerShell.&nbsp; The intellisense is great and has all the things you were expect when debugging through scripts.</p> <p><strong>Miscellaneous</strong></p> <p><a href="http://www.baremetalsoft.com/baretail/">BareTail</a>:&nbsp; Amazing program which watches log files in real time and can highlight rows based on a search pattern.</p> <p><a href="http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/scriptcenter/dd742419">PowerShell</a>/<a href="http://cygwin.org/">Cygwin</a>/<a href="http://www.mingw.org/wiki/MSYS">MSYS</a>:&nbsp; I used to be a Cygwin/MSYS user because back in the day I liked to install a different Linux distribution every week so I learned some basic Bash commands and that carried over to Windows.&nbsp; Since PowerShell now exists, we have a real shell in Windows, so I’ve switched over to learn it, since as a Windows developer it’s more applicable to the kind of work I do.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>And there’s more but that’s enough for now!</p>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>bling</div>
<div class='content'>
Actually, Cygwin/MSYS used to be in my tool chain, but I&#39;ve made an effort to learn PowerShell by making it my shell.<br /><br />I&#39;m still thrown off sometimes because PowerShell operates on objects, rather than text.  Sometimes this makes it easier, sometimes harder.  Grep comes to mind.<br /><br />Check out BareTail if you want to watch log files in real time.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mike McG</div>
<div class='content'>
Nice post! Gonna check out XAML Intellisense Presenter, All Margins, and PowerGUI.<br /><br />For Always on Top functionality, I&#39;ve relied on PowerMenu. It doesn&#39;t have the middle-click (gotta go through the app menu in the window chrome), but it also lets you Minimize to Tray. StexBar is also pretty neat-o, lets you create your own buttons on the Explorer button bar.<br /><br />Maybe due to my *nix background, I also install Cygwin (including sshd which allows me to use Cygwin through PuTTY rather than cmd.exe), grepWin (regular expression per-directory content search), and Tail for Win32 (to watch log files). (In addition to Tail I install Less for Windows and hook it up to StexBar, then use Shift+F to watch files).</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[That Commenting Thing]]></title>
    <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/2011/03/10/that-commenting-thing/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bling.github.io//blog/2011/03/10/that-commenting-thing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I’m working on a project right now that has near 99% of its code commented.&nbsp; Wow, that’s impressive!&nbsp; Actually, it’s more scary…even some of the private fields are commented….</p> <p>At one point, someone decided that it was a good idea to impose <em>some</em> kind of standard rather than none, so they recommended <a href="http://archive.msdn.microsoft.com/sourceanalysis">StyleCop</a> with all of its default settings, including requiring comments on everything.</p> <p>This seemed like a good idea, and it probably was, until someone found <a href="http://submain.com/products/ghostdoc.aspx">GhostDoc</a>.&nbsp; The plugin definitely gives off that “cool” factor the first time you use it.&nbsp; Wow, with a single key stroke it automagically documented all of my code!!!&nbsp; The problem, and it’s a pretty big one, is that it generates documentation based on the name of the properties, names, and class.&nbsp; Surely if it can do that, you, a much more sophisticated machine, can do that!</p> <p>Alas, the code base ended up getting GhostDocced to death all over the place to the point where I was driven mad and insane that I spent the time to write a VS2010 extension to purposely hide these comments.&nbsp; I’m talking about comments like this:</p> <p><a href="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/TXmZSvlTRnI/AAAAAAAAADQ/hk3vTlVJ5Jc/s1600-h/image%5B4%5D.png"><img style="background-image: none; border-bottom: 0px; border-left: 0px; padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; display: inline; border-top: 0px; border-right: 0px; padding-top: 0px" title="image" border="0" alt="image" src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/TXmZSurQc8I/AAAAAAAAADU/NCeYxDgaINc/image_thumb%5B2%5D.png?imgmax=800" width="505" height="156"></a></p> <p>The comments add absolutely <strong>no value</strong> and IMO <strong>makes it harder to read</strong>, and has the added deficit that if for whatever reason someone changes the name property, chances are they will forget to update the comments.&nbsp; It gets worse with WCF service contracts with many parameters.</p> <p>So yes, it frustrated me enough that I took some spare time to write an extension to shrink those damn XML comments to such a small size it doesn’t bother me anymore, like this:</p> <p><a href="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/TXmZS7pHAXI/AAAAAAAAADY/IV53KxtUWUQ/s1600-h/image%5B8%5D.png"><img style="background-image: none; border-bottom: 0px; border-left: 0px; padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; display: inline; border-top: 0px; border-right: 0px; padding-top: 0px" title="image" border="0" alt="image" src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/TXmZTTUjF0I/AAAAAAAAADc/h96-4zUY6oM/image_thumb%5B4%5D.png?imgmax=800" width="566" height="200"></a></p> <p>You can grab the code off <a href="https://github.com/bling/XmlCommentShrink">GitHub</a>.</p>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>bling</div>
<div class='content'>
Originally I tried to use code folding to solve the problem, but the best thing that comes built-in is collapsing to definitions (Ctrl+M/O), which will fold everything.  But that also folds the methods as well, so then I&#39;d have to manually unfold them, which quickly got tiresome.<br /><br />The optimal solution I think would be for the extension to automatically collapse only the comments when you open a file, but that is much more complex than just changing the font size....maybe an exercise for another weekend when I&#39;m bored with nothing to do...</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Vsevolod Parfenov</div>
<div class='content'>
Why don&#39;t you fold them instead of changing font size?</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fixing ReSharper 5 EAP Missing Colors]]></title>
    <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/2009/11/07/fixing-resharper-5-eap-missing-colors/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bling.github.io//blog/2009/11/07/fixing-resharper-5-eap-missing-colors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think anyone’s who has used ReSharper for an extended period of time has experienced the colors disappearing all of a sudden from Fonts &amp; Colors.  This is excruciatingly annoying when I have a dark color scheme set up and the colors disappear on me.</p>

<p>In the case of RS5, it seems even more flakey than RS4, and installing/uninstalling other addins have a pretty high probability of losing the colors, and this time, repairing the installation doesn’t fix the problem (nor does the registry restore trick).</p>

<p>For me, to fix the problem I had to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Uninstall RS5.</li>
<li>Install RS4.5</li>
<li>Open VS!!!</li>
<li>Go into settings, and verify all the colors are in Fonts &amp; Colors.</li>
<li>Upgrade to RS5.</li>
</ul>


<p>If you skip opening VS, it will not restore colors&hellip;at least it didn’t when I tried it.  Following the above fixed it for me in 2 occasions already.  If Jetbrains sees this blog post, PLEASE fix this extremely annoying bug.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dark Color Refresh]]></title>
    <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/2009/09/27/dark-color-refresh/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bling.github.io//blog/2009/09/27/dark-color-refresh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/Sqh4cikBOcI/AAAAAAAAABA/9NgFoJ5lIuA/s1600-h/colorscheme.png"><img style="text-align: center; margin: 0px 15px 10px 0px; width: 252px; display: inline; height: 400px; cursor: hand" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5379682186603608514" border="0" alt="" align="left" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/Sqh4cikBOcI/AAAAAAAAABA/9NgFoJ5lIuA/s400/colorscheme.png" /></a> There you have it!&#160; I started with Visual Studio’s default settings and configured each and every color one by one.&#160; 3 hours later I was finished and satisfied with what I have…but I think it was time well spent considering this is what I’m looking at for &gt;= 8 hours a day.</p>  <p>This was a complete re-do of my previous dark theme.&#160; This one is even more colorful than the <a href="http://blingcode.blogspot.com/2008/09/importance-of-color-schemes.html">previous</a>, mainly because <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/resharper/index.html">Resharper</a> does an amazing job of detecting additional code elements like mutable vs unmutable, or unused code, in additional to many other things.</p>  <p>By the way, you should definitely spend the time to configure your own colors rather than using someone else’s template.&#160; The reason being is that each and every person is different, and obviously will have preferences towards different colors.&#160; I go through different moods and I’ll tweak the theme to be “blue” or “red” for a period of time.</p>  <p>Another reason why you configure it manually is that it drills into your brain more of what each color represents.&#160; If you just used my template you would probably never notice that orange means input parameter, and green is a local variable.</p>  <p>However, one thing you can and should take from this blog post is<strong> not to use pure black or pure white as your background </strong>(did you notice my current line indicator is darker than my background?).&#160; Set your background to (10,10,10) or (245,245,245).&#160; <em>Your eyes will thank me.</em></p>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
