<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: logging | bling on software development]]></title>
  <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/categories/logging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bling.github.io//"/>
  <updated>2013-06-30T17:16:54+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bling.github.io//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bailey Ling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Injecting Logger Instances Via Convention With Unity]]></title>
    <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/2011/08/19/injecting-logger-instances-via-unity/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bling.github.io//blog/2011/08/19/injecting-logger-instances-via-unity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s say you have something like this:
``` csharp
public void MyClass {</p>

<pre><code>public ILog Logger { get; set; }
</code></pre>

<p>}
<code>``
And you simply want Unity to inject an instance of</code>ILog<code>such that its name is</code>requestingDependency.GetType().FullName<code>, which in this case would be</code>Full.Namespace.MyClass`.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll leave it up to the exercise of the reader, but if you search for &lsquo;log4net and Unity&rsquo; you will find some working solutions which IMO are way too long to solve this.  I have obviously taken for granted the features of Windsor and Autofac too much because I expected something like this to be easily done in 2-3 lines of code.</p>

<p>After a lot of cursing I&rsquo;ve come up with something that&rsquo;s almost as short and gets the job done:
``` csharp
public class LoggingExtension : UnityContainerExtension
{</p>

<pre><code>protected override void Initialize()
{
    this.Context.Strategies.AddNew(UnityBuildStage.PreCreation);
}
private class LogBuilderStrategy : BuilderStrategy
{
    private readonly Stack buildKeys = new Stack();
    public override void PreBuildUp(IBuilderContext context)
    {
        var type = ((NamedTypeBuildKey)context.BuildKey).Type;
        if (type == typeof(ILog))
        {
            if (this.buildKeys.Count &lt; 1)
                throw new InvalidOperationException("Log instances cannot be resolved directly.");
            context.Existing = LogManager.GetLog(this.buildKeys.Peek());
        }
        this.buildKeys.Push(type);
    }
    public override void PostBuildUp(IBuilderContext context)
    {
        this.buildKeys.Pop();
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
<code>``
If you noticed, I had to cast to</code>NamedTypeBuildKey`, which unfortunately means I’m still stuck with Unity 1.2&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Real World Performance Comparison: Enterprise Library Logging Block vs log4net]]></title>
    <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/2009/11/23/real-world-performance-comparison/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bling.github.io//blog/2009/11/23/real-world-performance-comparison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Any search on the web you find will consistently show log4net outperforming EL by a factor of around 4:1.&nbsp; Most of these tests are typically tight for/loops, and comments will end up saying things like “oh well that’s not a realistic test” or “well you shouldn’t be logging that much anyway”, etc etc.&nbsp; Well, let’s see how important choosing your logging infrastructure is in terms of overall system performance in a multithreaded application.<br />
<br />
One of my recent tasks was hunting down a memory leak.&nbsp; So I downloaded the trial of the ANTS .NET Bundle which contains a memory profiler and performance profiler.&nbsp; Hunting the memory leak was a pain since I wasn’t the one who wrote the code, so it took a while for me to realize which objects were “leaked.”&nbsp; I eventually found it, and then I turned my attention to using the performance profiler to see if any obvious places could be optimized.<br />
<br />
At this point I decided to swap in the Enterprise Logging Block to see how it would fair.&nbsp; The logging migration project was still in progress, and we haven’t made the full switch yet, but I figured I should try out it anyway because I’m the curious type.<br />
<br />
The software already uses the Trace diagnostics extensively.&nbsp; Practically every message, error, you name it, will get Trace.WriteLined…and then a LogFileWriter will pick it up, and dump it to a file.&nbsp; In my testing, I simply added an extra line of code here, namely Logger.Write(LogEntry).&nbsp; Thus, anything that used to get logged, will also get logged by the EL.<br />
<br />
Then, it was basically running the application to a similar set of scenarios, and then seeing what the profiler says.&nbsp; Obviously each run will not be exactly the same as the previous, but overall I think if we look at percentages we can begin to see where the CPU is taking the most time. <br />
<br />
Here is what the application does without any modifications.<br />
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/SwojFG6Z-bI/AAAAAAAAABs/JOlmoVHku8c/s1600/1.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/SwojFG6Z-bI/AAAAAAAAABs/JOlmoVHku8c/s320/1.png" /></a><br />
</div>Here is the application after adding Logger.Write(LogEntry).<br />
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/SwojGq9R6FI/AAAAAAAAAB0/l899yhPm5a0/s1600/2.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/SwojGq9R6FI/AAAAAAAAAB0/l899yhPm5a0/s320/2.png" /></a><br />
</div><br />
Yeah, I was pretty surprised too.&nbsp; That one method ended up being the most expensive method in the entire application.<br />
<br />
A quick look at the source revealed quite a bit of code dedicated to thread safety.&nbsp; So digging deeper, I decided to avoid the static Logger.Write method altogether, create instance LogWriters directly, and have them all go to a singleton FileTraceListener.<br />
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/SwojH5vrfYI/AAAAAAAAAB8/bKYT18Hdx-8/s1600/3.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/SwojH5vrfYI/AAAAAAAAAB8/bKYT18Hdx-8/s320/3.png" /></a><br />
</div>That’s a noticeable improvement…it’s not #1 anymore.&nbsp; The CPU time also dropped from ~15% to ~10%.&nbsp; That means that ~5% of CPU time was in the static Logger.Write(LogEntry) method.&nbsp; If you look at the graphs you’ll notice a common pattern among them, because I wanted to test with the same scenario to get as close to as measurable results as possible…but to illustrate how bad the EL’s performance can get, here’s one:<br />
<br />
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/SwojJLBz2KI/AAAAAAAAACE/FI3Sl-wNhmE/s1600/4.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/SwojJLBz2KI/AAAAAAAAACE/FI3Sl-wNhmE/s320/4.png" /></a><br />
</div><br />
I literally fell off my chair when I first discovered this as I didn’t think it could be possible something that’s supposed to be non-invasive could end up taking this much CPU.&nbsp; This is one of the earlier tests I did where&nbsp; I didn't have a set scenario yet.<br />
<br />
And of course, here are the results with log4net.<br />
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/SwojKotCNLI/AAAAAAAAACM/jhlHy7LvZyc/s1600/5.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_WZr-_wsEf1c/SwojKotCNLI/AAAAAAAAACM/jhlHy7LvZyc/s320/5.png" /></a><br />
</div><br />
So what does that leave us?<br />
<br />
log4net:&nbsp; 5%<br />
EL static:&nbsp; 15%<br />
EL instance:&nbsp; 10%<br />
<br />
So what should you get out of this?&nbsp; Be very careful of how you invoke Logger.Write()…it may not be as cheap as you think it is.&nbsp; Even log4net took much more CPU time than I expected.<br />
<br />
I redid the test using Castle’s logging framework, which is a barebones dump messages to a file.&nbsp; The total CPU time for this was 0.016%.&nbsp; Yep!&nbsp; I had to scroll down to even find it!<br />
<br />
I guess this shows that even log4net, which is touted for high-performance, comes at a cost.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
