<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vim | bling on software development]]></title>
  <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/categories/vim/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bling.github.io//"/>
  <updated>2013-06-30T22:45:46+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bling.github.io//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bailey Ling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unite.vim, The plugin you didn't know you need]]></title>
    <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/2013/06/02/unite-dot-vim-the-plugin-you-didnt-know-you-need/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-02T19:34:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bling.github.io//blog/2013/06/02/unite-dot-vim-the-plugin-you-didnt-know-you-need</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1><a href="https://github.com/Shougo/unite.vim">Unite.vim</a></h1>

<p>What is this?  If you&rsquo;ve never heard of this Vim plugin, then this post is for you.  This is one of those hidden gems in the Vim plugin world that is truly life changing.  I think this plugin is so awesome that I&rsquo;ve decided to write a post dedicated to it so that more people know about it.</p>

<p>The plugin is written by <a href="https://github.com/Shougo">Shougo Matsu</a>.  He has written a lot of other popular plugins, notably <a href="https://github.com/Shougo/neocomplcache.vim">neocomplcache</a> and <a href="https://github.com/Shougo/vimshell.vim">vimshell</a>.  I use a lot of his plugins, so I started to notice when certain plugins started using Unite as a dependency, like <a href="https://github.com/Shougo/neobundle.vim">neobundle</a> and <a href="https://github.com/Shougo/vimfiler.vim">vimfiler</a>.</p>

<p>At first it looked like Unite was just a general purpose library, but I was in for a surprise because it is so much more than that.</p>

<!--more-->


<h1>What is it?</h1>

<p>This is the problem I had initially.  The project <a href="https://github.com/Shougo/unite.vim">homepage</a> describes it as &ldquo;&hellip;can search and display information from arbitrary sources like files, buffers, recently used files or registers.&rdquo;  It goes on to show some usage samples, but there is no &ldquo;wow&rdquo; factor.  After reading the readme I still didn&rsquo;t have a clue what the plugin could do.</p>

<p>It wasn&rsquo;t until I stumbled upon terryma&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/terryma/dotfiles/blob/master/.vimrc">vimrc</a> (the author of <a href="https://github.com/terryma/vim-multiple-cursors">multiple-cursors</a> and realized that he replaced <a href="https://github.com/kien/ctrlp.vim">ctrlp</a> entirely with unite).  ctrlp is by far one of the best/most popular plugins and for it to be replacable is no easy feat.</p>

<p>So how do you do it?</p>

<h1>First things first, configuration</h1>

<p>Unite is geared towards experienced vim users &mdash; it does not create any bindings by default.  To make any use of it, you will need to create the bindings yourself.  And in certain cases, rather than declaring <code>g:variables</code>, you configure it with method calls, like <code>unite#filters#matcher_default#use(['matcher_fuzzy'])</code>, but thankfully, like all of Shougo&rsquo;s plugins, the plugin is <em>very</em> well documented, so feel free to <code>:help unite</code> to figure out how to use the plugin.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re lazy, you can go directly to my <a href="https://github.com/bling/dotvim">vim distribution</a> and take the configuration out of there.</p>

<p>But enough talking, here&rsquo;s some quick demos of what Unite can do&hellip;</p>

<h1>What can it do?</h1>

<h2>File searching like <a href="https://github.com/kien/ctrlp.vim">ctrlp.vim</a></h2>

<p><code>
nnoremap &lt;C-p&gt; :Unite file_rec/async&lt;cr&gt;
</code></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/unite-ctrlp.gif"></p>

<p>Did you notice the async flag?  Unite uses <a href="https://github.com/Shougo/vimproc.vim">vimproc</a> behind the scenes, which affords for searching while it populates the file list in the background.  That is amazing!</p>

<h2>Content searching like <a href="https://github.com/mileszs/ack.vim">ack.vim</a> (or <a href="https://github.com/rking/ag.vim">ag.vim</a>)</h2>

<p><code>
nnoremap &lt;space&gt;/ :Unite grep:.&lt;cr&gt;
</code></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/unite-grep.gif"></p>

<p>Unite can be configured to use <code>grep</code>, <code>ack</code>, or <code>ag</code>; whichever is available.</p>

<h2>Yank history like <a href="https://github.com/vim-scripts/YankRing.vim">yankring</a>/<a href="https://github.com/maxbrunsfeld/vim-yankstack">yankstack</a></h2>

<p><code>
let g:unite_source_history_yank_enable = 1
nnoremap &lt;space&gt;y :Unite history/yank&lt;cr&gt;
</code></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/unite-yanks.gif"></p>

<p>To be fair, unite cannot bind to a key to cycle the history, so it&rsquo;s not a 100% replacement.  However, if you only rarely use the yankring then this is a pretty good alternative.</p>

<h2>Buffer switching like <a href="https://github.com/sjbach/lusty">LustyJuggler</a></h2>

<p><code>
nnoremap &lt;space&gt;s :Unite -quick-match buffer&lt;cr&gt;
</code></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/unite-juggle.gif"></p>

<p>Notice that <code>-quick-match</code> is just a flag, which means you can apply this to any source.</p>

<h2>Bonus</h2>

<p>Ever been jealous of Sublime&rsquo;s auto preview feature?  Well, turns out unite has an <code>-auto-preview</code> flag that you can add.</p>

<h1>Finale</h1>

<p>And that&rsquo;s all I got for now.  I&rsquo;m still learning more about what this plugin can do, but it&rsquo;s definitely earned its place in my vim toolbox.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing Macros with Vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/2013/02/11/writing-macros-with-vim/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bling.github.io//blog/2013/02/11/writing-macros-with-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First, let’s start with a Javascript function:
``` javascript
function foo(hello, world,</p>

<pre><code>         how, are,
         you) {
</code></pre>

<p>}
<code>
Now let’s convert that to the following:
</code> javascript
function foo(parameters) {</p>

<pre><code>var hello = parameters.hello;
var world = parameters.world;
var how = parameters.how;
var are = parameters.are;
var you = parameters.you;
</code></pre>

<p>}
<code>
Here are the macros I used to do this:
</code> vim
let @r=&lsquo;di(iparameters^[/{^M2o^[kpg<code>[v</code>]Jgv:s/\s//g<sup>M0</sup>:try|exe &ldquo;norm! @q&rdquo;|endtry<sup>MA</sup>;^[V:s/,/;\r/g<sup>Mv</sup>``=&rsquo;
let @q=&lsquo;ywivar ^[pa = parameters.^[f,^[l@q&rsquo;
```</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Note that if you copy paste the above into your vimrc it will not work. The <code>^[</code> and <code>^M</code> found are actually single characters, not two. To input this properly you will need to chord it in input mode with <code>&lt;Ctrl-V&gt;</code>. So for <code>&lt;Esc&gt;</code> you would chord <code>&lt;Ctrl+V&gt;&lt;Ctrl+[&gt;</code>.</p>

<p>So, when I&rsquo;m inside the parameters of the function, I can hit <code>@r</code> and it will perform the refactoring. Now let’s break it down step by step.</p>

<h1>@q The first macro</h1>

<p>This is a recursive macro which takes something like <code>a,b,c</code> and turns it into <code>var a = p.a,var b = p.b,var c = p.c</code>. Let’s see how that’s done.</p>

<ol>
<li><code>yw</code> <code>i</code> <code>var</code> <code>&lt;Esc&gt;</code> <code>p</code> Yanks the word and enter insert mode, type var, exit insert mode and paste the just yanked word.</li>
<li><code>a = parameters.</code> Append and fill in parameters.</li>
<li><code>&lt;Esc&gt;</code> <code>f</code>, <code>l</code> Exit insert mode, find the next <code>,</code></li>
<li><code>l</code> <code>@q</code> Adjust the cursor position and recursively call itself.</li>
</ol>


<p>Recursive macros terminate when the first error occurs. In this macro, that error is when there are no more commas left.</p>

<h1>@r The second macro</h1>

<p>The is the macro that should be invoked, and references the <code>@q</code> macro.</p>

<ol>
<li><code>di(</code> Deletes everything inside the brackets.</li>
<li><code>i</code> parameters Enter insert mode and type parameters.</li>
<li><code>&lt;Esc&gt;</code> <code>/{</code> <code>&lt;CR&gt;</code> Leaves insert mode and finds the next brace.</li>
<li><code>2o</code> <code>&lt;Esc&gt;</code> <code>k</code> <code>p</code> Creates two empty lines and pastes what we deleted into the first line.</li>
<li><code>g`[v`]</code> <code>J</code> Visually select what we just pasted and join them all into a single line.</li>
<li><code>gv</code> <code>:s/\s//g</code> <code>&lt;CR&gt;</code> Reselect the visually and delete all whitespace.</li>
<li><code>0</code> Move to the beginning of the line.</li>
<li><code>:try|exe "norm! @q"|endtry</code> <code>&lt;CR&gt;</code> Macros will terminate on the first error, even if referencing another macro. Wrapping the other macro with try|endtry swallows the error and lets the current macro continue.</li>
<li><code>A;</code> <code>&lt;Esc&gt;</code> Append ; to the end of the line.</li>
<li><code>V</code> <code>:s/,/;\r/g</code> <code>&lt;CR&gt;</code> Visually select the line, replace with carriage returns.</li>
<li><code>v=``</code>  Visually select from the current cursor position back to where it was originally was, and format.</li>
</ol>


<p>Now is this the best way to do it? Probably not. I would not be surprised if someone was able to do it with less keystrokes or a single macro.  But hey, it was fun learning experience, and ultimately I turned all of that into two keystrokes that can be reused many times.</p>

<p>I posted this on <a href="http://vimgolf.com/challenges/511991607729fb0002000003">vimgolf</a> so let’s see how other people solved the same refactoring!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Love Affair with Vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/2013/02/10/love-affair-with-vim/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bling.github.io//blog/2013/02/10/love-affair-with-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It wasn&rsquo;t too long ago when I was a full-time C# developer and my environment was Visual Studio eight hours a day.  Then, I became a web developer over night cold turkey writing Javascript and CSS.  It&rsquo;s one of the benefits of working for a consulting company.</p>

<p>You might think what does that have to do with the title of this post?  Well, originally my plan was to write a blog post contrasting on the differences between Javascript and C#, as well as the development environments and deployment platforms.  But really, what I really wanted to write about was Vim.</p>

<p>Moving from Visual Studio to Vim was a progression through different editors and environments.  The first thing I used to write Javascript was Webstorm.  Over time I realized that you didn&rsquo;t really need an IDE to write Javascript/CSS.  Then, I used Sublime Text for a little bit.  But ultimately, I settled on Vim, and stayed there.</p>

<p>My stubbornness turned out to be beneficial when I was learning Vim because the first month was absolutely painful.  I remapped all of my arrows keys to do nothing to force myself to use hjkl.  Eventually I got the hang of it, and now I definitely have the muscle memory that makes me much more productive when editing (and reading) text.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>By default Vim is just a text editor.  But I work on a project, so like most lazy people I searched for prepackaged plugins and came across two popular distributions: <a href="https://github.com/spf13/spf13-vim">spf13</a> and <a href="https://github.com/carlhuda/janus">janus</a>.  When I installed them, it was like someone took over Vim and made it change into a completely different beast.  I didn&rsquo;t know how to use it anymore.</p>

<p>I took a step back.  I forgot where I got this advice, but I think anyone using Vim needs to do this: <em>start your own vimrc from scratch</em>.</p>

<p>I took a look at all the settings that spf13 and janus changed.  I copied them to my vimrc <em>one by one</em>, and also <code>:help</code>ing each setting so that I knew exactly what it changed.  I must say, Vim&rsquo;s documentation is some of the best and most comprehensive of any tool I&rsquo;ve worked with.  It was incredibly helpful in my progression.</p>

<p>Then, I did the same thing for plugins.  And the nice thing was that most plugins followed the Vim pattern of having good documentation.  After installing <code>fooplugin</code>, I just <code>:help fooplugin</code> and I got all the information I needed to know about the plugin.</p>

<p>I became obsessed with optimizing my vimrc, and trying out different plugins on a daily basis.  And because I was very adamant with trying one plugin at a time, I got to know them very well.  I knew about how to turn certain settings on and off, how to configure their bindings, and more importantly, how it interacted with all of the other plugins I have already installed.  Over time my vimrc became a full blown distribution in its own right, highly customized to my personal work habits.</p>

<p>However, even though I recommend that anyone interested in taking their Vim skills to the next level should do this discovery that I have done, there are certainly classes of plugins that I deem to be <em>must-have</em> for any Vim user and I wanted to highlight them here.</p>

<h1>Plugin Management</h1>

<p>First things first you will need one plugin to rule them all!  <a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-pathogen">Pathogen</a> changed the way people install plugins by utilizing git submodules.  This has the pros and cons of git submodules, i.e. they track a specific version of the external git repository, so if external plugins are updated frequently you have to manually update all your submodules.</p>

<p>However, more often than not, you just want the latest version.  <a href="https://github.com/gmarik/vundle">Vundle</a> takes the management one step further and will automatically grab source code from Github for you (as well as automatically updating everything to the latest version).</p>

<p>The last one and least known is <a href="https://github.com/Shougo/neobundle.vim">NeoBundle</a>, which is like Vundle on steroids.  It adds a whole ton of new features like allowing you to specify installation steps for compiling something.</p>

<h1>Fuzzy File Searching</h1>

<p>This was the major game changer for me and changed the way I worked.  Naturally, proper Vim technique forces your hands to be on the home row, which makes reaching for the mouse (or even the arrow keys) to be inefficient.  Therefore, the fastest way to open a file is usually to type its name.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/wincent/Command-T">CommandT</a> (written in Ruby) is noticeably much faster than <a href="https://github.com/kien/ctrlp.vim">CtrlP</a> (pure VimScript), but CtrlP has a lot more features.  There&rsquo;s also <a href="http://www.vim.org/scripts/script.php?script_id=1984">FuzzyFinder</a>, which I have not tried.</p>

<h1>Autocomplete and Snippets</h1>

<p>There are various contenders here.  Generally, you&rsquo;ll find that people fall into two camps.</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://github.com/garbas/vim-snipmate">Snipmate</a>/<a href="https://github.com/SirVer/ultisnips">UltiSnips</a> + <a href="https://github.com/ervandew/supertab">SuperTab</a> + <a href="http://www.vim.org/scripts/script.php?script_id=1879">AutoComplPop</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Shougo/neocomplcache">neocomplcache</a> + <a href="https://github.com/Shougo/neosnippet">neosnippet</a></li>
</ol>


<p>Snipmate is an older implementation of snippets which is getting replaced with UltiSnips.  Supertab gives you an easy way to trigger omnicompletion with (you guessed it) tab, and AutoComplPop is for automatically showing the popup as you type.</p>

<p>Neocomplcache is a very powerful completion plugin.  It runs a little slower than SuperTab because it does a lot more, but I find the performance acceptable so that&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;m using.  And I choose neosnippet over the others simply because it&rsquo;s by the same author and thus has better integration (e.g. available snippets will appear in the list).</p>

<p>And of course, a good collection of snippets like <a href="https://github.com/honza/vim-snippets">honza</a>&rsquo;s collection.</p>

<p><em>edit</em>: Since I last posted this another autocomplete plugin has taken the Vim world by storm.  It is none other than <a href="https://github.com/Valloric/YouCompleteMe">YouCompleteMe</a>.  This is a fantastic plugin which shows a lot of promise.  It does not have as many features as neocomplcache yet, but it is improving every day and has a large community gathering around it.  Things can only get better!</p>

<p><em>edit 2</em>: <a href="https://github.com/Shougo/neocomplete.vim">neocomplete</a> is the next generation version of neocomplcache, and despite being in its infancy is showing great progress and has most (if not all) of the features of neocomplcache.  It requires you to recompile vim with lua support, but has the added benefit that it is way faster than before, and unlike YouCompleteMe (which officially does not support Windows), it works very well on Windows as well.</p>

<h1>And that&rsquo;s it!</h1>

<p>What?!  No file browser?  No buffer manager?  Yes, I have all of those installed as well.  In fact, I have over 50 plugins installed in total.  But in my opinion, they are not <em>killer</em> features.  I can live without them.  But if I didn&rsquo;t have fuzzy searching or completion/snippets, I would feel a little too naked.</p>

<p>Out of the box Vim has some interesting defaults, mainly for backwards compatibility with Vi, but I think it&rsquo;s safe to say that anyone who uses Vim seriously will have a custom vimrc.  If you&rsquo;re just starting out and don&rsquo;t know what to change, <a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-sensible">sensible</a> is a good set of defaults.</p>

<p>Vim has changed my work habits dramatically.  I think and dream Vim.  I install Vim plugins in my browsers.  And every day, she still teaches me new tricks.  It&rsquo;s quite exhilarating!</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve read until this point you might be interested in the full set of plugins that I&rsquo;m using.  If so, head over to my <a href="http://bling.github.com/dotvim/">vim distribution project</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
