<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: emacs | bling on software development]]></title>
  <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/categories/emacs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bling.github.io//"/>
  <updated>2013-09-10T01:59:40+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://bling.github.io//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bailey Ling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim in Emacs Bootstrap]]></title>
    <link href="http://bling.github.io//blog/2013/09/09/vim-in-emacs-bootstrap/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-09T20:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://bling.github.io//blog/2013/09/09/vim-in-emacs-bootstrap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Did I wake up on the wrong side of the bed?</p>

<p>My New Year&rsquo;s resolution for 2013 was to learn Vim. I was so new to Vim that I did not even know how to <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/14107198/vim-delete-whitespace-between-2-lines">join lines</a> properly. However, I was diligent, patient, and stubborn enough to stick at it. It didn&rsquo;t take long for me to <a href="http://bling.github.io/blog/2013/02/10/love-affair-with-vim">fall in love</a>. I even ended up writing a <a href="https://github.com/bling/vim-airline">plugin</a> for Vim that got so popular that I was writing VimL as a second job.</p>

<p>Sounds like I&rsquo;m pretty happy with Vim (and I am), so why am I trying Emacs?</p>

<p>Curiosity is a major reason. But more I think the philosophy of Emacs fits my personality better. The Vim community is very much divided into two camps: the text editor people, and the people who try to turn Vim into an IDE. I am in the latter. My vim <a href="https://github.com/bling/dotvim">distribution</a> has over 90 plugins. While I haven&rsquo;t yet run into Vim&rsquo;s limitations of trying to use it this way, I can already see the walls coming up&hellip;</p>

<p>But here&rsquo;s the thing, I&rsquo;m addicted to <strong>modal editing</strong>, not Vim.<!-- more --> It just so happens that Vim is the best implementation of modal editing, but Emacs has something that does a pretty damn good job too! And it&rsquo;s none other than <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/Evil">evil-mode</a>.</p>

<p>With evil-mode, it&rsquo;s finally possible to have the best of both worlds. The power of modal editing with the near limitless extensibility of Emacs.</p>

<p>And as an added bonus I can finally have an excuse to learn a Lisp dialect. I discovered with Vim that customizing your editor is an incredible catalyst for learning a new language. It wasn&rsquo;t my intention to memorize a sizable portion of the VimL standard library when I started using Vim, but it happened anyway once I started tweaking and customizing&hellip;</p>

<p>My goal is that by the end of this post you&rsquo;ll have a working Emacs installation with Vim keybindings out of the box.</p>

<h1>Back to Basics</h1>

<p>The best way to learn is to start from scratch. And so I did exactly that starting with the built-in tutorial <code>C-h t</code>. While the purpose of this blog post is to get modal editing working in Emacs, you&rsquo;re not going to be able to make <em>everything</em> modal, so you still need to know basic commands to navigate around.</p>

<h1>Things you need to know</h1>

<p>There are a couple important Emacs keys that you should know.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>C-g</code> is the universal &ldquo;get me out of here&rdquo; key, equivalent to <code>C-c</code> in Vim.</li>
<li><code>C-h</code> is the &ldquo;help&rdquo; prefix. <code>C-h C-h</code> will show you all possible options. I&rsquo;ve found that I use <code>C-h f</code> very often, which is used to lookup help for functions.</li>
<li><code>C-x</code> is a also very important, as it&rsquo;s the prefix for many common things like saving and finding files.</li>
<li><code>C-c</code> by <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/html_node/elisp/Key-Binding-Conventions.html">convention</a> are used for many things, including the equivalent of <code>&lt;leader&gt;</code> for user customizations when followed by letters, but also for major and minor mode bindings.</li>
</ul>


<h1>Setting up your &ldquo;vimrc&rdquo;</h1>

<p>In Emacs, this is the <code>~/.emacs</code> file. But just like in Vim, where you usually have a <code>~/.vim</code> directory for various plugins and configuration, Emacs has the <code>~/.emacs.d</code> directory. As an added bonus, <code>~/.emacs.d/init.el</code> is automatically loaded, so if you put your dotfiles up on GitHub it&rsquo;s as simple as cloning it to <code>~/.emacs.d</code>.</p>

<h1>What&rsquo;s with the (((())))?</h1>

<p>Going through the documentation is one thing, but making the first change to your <code>~/.emacs.d/init.el</code> file is daunting, at least for me it was. While Vim also has its own scripting language, VimL, it is much more newbie friendly.</p>

<p>How do you turn on line numbers? You add <code>set number</code> to your vimrc. It&rsquo;s simple, straightforward, and obvious. You don&rsquo;t even know you&rsquo;re scripting in Vim; it just looks like a configuration file at this point. How do you do that in Emacs? First you search on Google, which links you to this <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/LineNumbers">EmacsWiki</a> article. If that doesn&rsquo;t scare you from using Emacs I don&rsquo;t know what will.</p>

<p>The short answer is, you add <code>(global-linum-mode t)</code> to your <code>init.el</code> file. Right off the bat the questions would be, is that a variable, a function? What is <code>t</code>?</p>

<p>Configuring Emacs throws you into Lisp from the get go, so what you want to do is actually read <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/eintr.html">Introduction to Programming in Emacs Lisp</a>.</p>

<h1>Lisp basics</h1>

<p>You&rsquo;re going to be seeing a lot of Lisp, so let&rsquo;s summarize the basics:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>set</code> will set a variable, but you will rarely see this.</li>
<li><code>setq</code> is <em>very</em> frequently seen. The q stands for quote, which will sidetrack you to understanding what a <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/134887/when-to-use-quote-in-lisp">quote</a> is.</li>
<li><code>setq-default</code> sets a variable if it&rsquo;s not already set/overridden.</li>
<li><code>defun</code> defines a function.</li>
<li><code>-p</code> by convention is added to functions that return true or false (the p stands for predicate).</li>
</ul>


<p>Now that things are a bit more readable, we can begin setting up our configuration to get evil-mode installed.</p>

<h1>Package management</h1>

<p>Emacs 24 comes with built-in <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/ELP">package management</a>. The default GNU repository doesn&rsquo;t really have many packages, but luckily there&rsquo;s a community driven repository named <a href="http://melpa.milkbox.net/">MELPA</a> where up to date packages are built directly from GitHub.</p>

<p>So, let&rsquo;s add the MELPA into our <code>~/.emacs.d/init.el</code> file:</p>

<p>``` cl
;;; this loads the package manager
(require &lsquo;package)</p>

<p>;;; here there&rsquo;s a variable named package-archives, and we are adding the MELPA repository to it
(add-to-list &lsquo;package-archives</p>

<pre><code>         '("melpa" . "http://melpa.milkbox.net/packages/") t)
</code></pre>

<p>;;; loads packages and activates them
(package-initialize)
```</p>

<p>OK, straightforward so far.</p>

<h1>Installing evil</h1>

<p>Next up is the all important <code>M-x</code> binding. This is sort of like Vim&rsquo;s <code>:</code> where you can type commands. Here we are going to do a <code>M-x package-refresh-contents RET</code>. In Emacs, <code>RET</code> is the convention for <code>&lt;CR&gt;</code>. This will refresh the repository of available packages. And finally, <code>M-x package-install RET evil RET</code>.</p>

<p>And now it&rsquo;s installed!</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not enabled by default, so we need to append the following lines to our <code>init.el</code> file:</p>

<p><code>cl
(require 'evil)
(evil-mode t)
</code></p>

<p>Finally, <code>C-x C-c</code> to quit Emacs and restart it. If you&rsquo;re feeling adventerous you can use <code>M-x eval-buffer RET</code> instead.</p>

<h1>Finale</h1>

<p>Congratulations! You have a working Emacs installation with Vim modal editing!</p>

<p>You may notice that in addition to <code>C-c</code>, <code>C-h</code>, and <code>C-x</code> that I mentioned earlier, <code>C-u</code> will not scroll up half a page as you would expect. This is because by default this is mapped to the Emacs <code>universal-argument</code> function, which is used for repeating. You can of course customize all of this, but I&rsquo;ll let you take it from here&hellip;</p>

<p>And so there you have it!</p>

<p>TLDR: <code>git clone https://github.com/bling/emacs-evil-bootstrap.git ~/.emacs.d</code> will automate this entire blog post and let you try Vim in Emacs in 10-20 seconds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
